Yannan (Nellie) Wu

606 Antioch Terrace, CA, 94085

Personal website: https://nellie-wu.github.io

Summary

I am a machine learning accelerator modeling engineer at Google. Before joining Google, I obtained my Ph.D. from MIT in computer architecture and systems. I have extensive research experience modeling and designing energy-efficient hardware accelerators for data and computation-intensive applications (such as deep neural networks), in both academic and industrial settings. My works have led to significant contributions to open-source industrial code bases, publications/tutorials at top-tier conferences (e.g., MICRO, ISCA), and a US patent application.

Education

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA

Email: nellieywu@gmail.com Mobile: +1-607-379-2186

 $\it Ph.D.$ in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (GPA: 5.0/5.0)

June 2023

M.S. in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (GPA: 5.0/5.0)

Feb. 2020

Advisors: Prof. Joel Emer (emer@csail.mit.edu) & Vivienne Sze (sze@mit.edu)

Cornell University

Ithaca, NY May. 2017

B.S. in Electrical & Computer Engineering (GPA: 4.02/4.3)

Skills

• C++, Python, C, Verilog, FPGA, PyTorch, MATLAB, HTML, Linux, Git, Docker, Synopsys Design Compiler Work Experience

• Google TPU Modeling Engineer

June, 2023 -

- Developed analytical modeling infrastructure for various components in TPU chips.
- Developed large language model training benchmarks in Tensorflow to aid TPU performance modeling.
- Performed co-design studies to improve TPU compute performance for large language models.

• NVIDIA Computer Architecture Research Intern

May 2021 - Aug. 2021

- Explored and analytically modeled various approaches to extend the existing Ampere GPU's sparse tensor core sparsity support to accelerate more structured sparsity patterns and structured sparsity degrees.
- Developed pruning and fine-tuning procedures using PyTorch to realize various sparsity structures.
- Filed a patent on a hardware-friendly and novel sparsity structure (US patent application number: 63/236,629).

• NVIDIA Computer Architecture Research Intern

May 2020 - Aug. 2020

- Integrated an energy estimation backend (developed at MIT) to NVIDIA's deep neural network accelerator models.
- Developed a statistical approach to analytically model the energy consumption of various sparse workloads (e.g., pruned deep neural networks).
- Implemented the proposed modeling flow in C++ and contributed to a large NVIDIA code base.

• Goldman Sachs Summer Technology Analyst

June 2016 - Aug. 2016

- Developed filtering functionalities for querying a database of balanced sheets.
- Developed a web front-end in JavaScript and HTML to allow user-friendly specification of the filter.

Teaching Experience

• MIT 6.825 Hardware Architecture for Deep Learning Lead TA

Jan. 2020 - May. 2020

• MIT 6.888 Hardware Architecture for Deep Learning TA (part-time)

Jan. 2019 - May. 2019

• Cornell ECE 3140 Embedded Systems TA

Jan. - May. 2016 & Aug.- Dec 2015

• Cornell ECE 2300 Digital Logic & Comp. Arch. TA

Jan. - May. 2015 & Aug. - Dec. 2014Jan. - May. 2015 & Aug. - Dec. 2014

Cornell MATH 1920 Multivariable Calc. Course Assistant
Cornell CS 1112 MATLAB Programming Course Consultant

Jan. 2014 - May. 2014

Selected Research Experience

• Software-Hardware Co-design with Novel DNN Sparsity Structures

MICRO23

- Proposed a systematic way to define various structured sparsity patterns used in DNN pruning and proposed a new class of structured sparsity patterns to represent a variety of sparsity degrees.
- Proposed a novel hardware design methodology to support the proposed structured sparsity patterns with light hardware overhead. Characterized the energy and area of important components with synthesized RTL.
- Developed pruning/fine-tuning procedures using PyTorch to realize the target sparsity structures in various DNNs.

• Analytical Modeling of Sparse Tensor Accelerators

ISPASS21, MICRO22, tutorial at ISCA21

- Proposed a taxonomy to systematically describe the previously unstructured and confusing design space of sparsity-related hardware optimizations proposed by existing sparse tensor accelerators.
- Proposed a decoupled methodology to statistically model sparse tensor accelerators by recognizing the orthogonality between several important design aspects.
- Developed an *open-source* fast, flexible and accurate modeling framework, **Sparseloop**, to enable design space exploration of sparse tensor accelerators. Contributed >40,000 lines of C++ code to an NVIDIA codebase.

• Flexible Energy and Area Estimation for Accelerator Designs

ICCAD19, ISPASS20

- Proposed a systematic and flexible methodology to describe accelerator architecture organizations.
- Based on the methodology, developed Accelergy, an open-source Python-based infrastructure for architecture-level (pre-RTL) energy and area estimation of accelerator designs.
- Developed several open-source prototype energy and area estimation plug-ins for Accelergy to showcase Accelergy's flexibility to understand user-provided, process-dependent data.

• Modeling of Fused-Layer DNN Accelerators

ISPASS23, TCASAI24

- Mentored a master student to understand the design space of fused-layer DNN processing.
- Participated in developing a methodology to systemically describe various fused-layer dataflows.
- Participated in developing an analytical modeling framework that analyzes the runtime activities of the hardware components in fused-layer accelerators.

Publications and Patent

- LoopTree: Exploring the Fused-layer Dataflow Accelerator Design Space Michael Gilbert, <u>Yannan Nellie Wu</u>, Angshuman Parashar, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Artificial Intelligence (TCASAI), Sep. 2024
- HighLight: Efficient and Flexible DNN Acceleration with Hierarchical Structured Sparsity Yannan Nellie Wu, Po-An Tsai, Saurav Muralidharan, Angshuman Parashar, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer *IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)*, Oct. 2023
- Accelerating Sparse Tensor Algebra by Overbooking Buffer Capacity Fisher Xue, Yannan Nellie Wu, Joel S. Emer, Vivienne Sze *IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)*, Oct. 2023
- LoopTree: Enabling Exploration of Fused-layer Dataflow Accelerators

 Michael Gilbert, Yannan Nellie Wu, Angshuman Parashar, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer

 IEEE International Symposium on Performance Analysis of Systems and Software (ISPASS), April 2023
- Sparseloop: An Analytical Approach to Sparse Tensor Accelerator Modeling
 <u>Yannan Nellie Wu</u>, Po-An Tsai, Angshuman Parashar, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer
 IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), Oct. 2022 (*Distinguished Artifact Award*)
- Architecture-Level Energy Estimation for Heterogeneous Computing Systems
 Francis Wang, Yannan Nellie Wu, Matthew Woicik, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer
 IEEE International Symposium on Performance Analysis of Systems and Software (ISPASS), March 2021
- Sparseloop: An Analytical, Energy-Focused Design Space Exploration Methodology for Sparse Tensor Accelerators

Yannan Nellie Wu, Po-An Tsai, Angshuman Parashar, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer IEEE International Symposium on Performance Analysis of Systems and Software (ISPASS), March 2021

- An Architecture-Level Energy and Area Estimator for Processing-In-Memory Accelerator Designs Yannan Nellie Wu, Vivienne Sze, Joel S. Emer IEEE International Symposium on Performance Analysis of Systems and Software (ISPASS), April 2020

Master Thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Feb. 2020

- Accelergy: An Architecture-Level Energy Estimation Methodology for Accelerator Designs Yannan Nellie Wu, Joel S. Emer, Vivienne Sze

 IEEE/ACM International Conference on Computer-Aided Design (ICCAD), Nov. 2019
- Pruning and Accelerating Neural Networks with Hierarchical Structured Sparsity Yannan Wu, Po-An Tsai, Saurav Muralidharan, Joel S. Emer US Patent Application Number: 63/236,629

Conference Tutorials

• Sparse Tensor Accelerators: Abstraction and Modeling

<u>Yannan Nellie Wu</u> with Joel S. Emer, Vivienne Sze, Po-An Tsai, and Angshuman Parashar *International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), June 2021*

• Tools for Evaluating Deep Neural Network Accelerator Designs

Yannan Nellie Wu with Joel S. Emer, Vivienne Sze, Angshuman Parashar, and Po-An Tsai

IEEE International Symposium on Performance Analysis of Systems and Software (ISPASS), Aug. 2020

International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), June 2020

IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), Oct. 2019

Selected Awards

• MICRO22 Distinguished Artifact Award

Awarded to ONE paper accepted to MICRO22 based on reproducibility of experimental results

Sept. 2017 - May. 2018

Oct. 2022

MIT Jacob's Presidential FellowshipCornell ECE Early Career Scholarship

June. 2014 - Aug. 2014